<chapter xml:id="cll_chapter9">
  <title>Chapter 9 To Boston Via The Road Go I, With An Excursion Into The Land Of Modals</title>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section1">
    <title>Introductory</title>
    <para>The basic type of Lojban sentence is the bridi: a claim by the speaker that certain objects are related in a certain way. The objects are expressed by Lojban grammatical forms called 
    <quote>sumti</quote>; the relationship is expressed by the Lojban grammatical form called a 
    <quote>selbri</quote>.</para>
    <para>The sumti are not randomly associated with the selbri, but according to a systematic pattern known as the 
    <quote>place structure</quote>of the selbri. This chapter describes the various ways in which the place structure of Lojban bridi is expressed and by which it can be manipulated. The place structure of a selbri is a sequence of empty slots into which the sumti associated with that selbri are placed. The sumti are said to occupy the places of the selbri.</para>
    <para>For our present purposes, every selbri is assumed to have a well-known place structure. If the selbri is a brivla, the place structure can be looked up in a dictionary (or, if the brivla is a lujvo not in any dictionary, inferred from the principles of lujvo construction as explained in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter12" />); if the selbri is a tanru, the place structure is the same as that of the final component in the tanru.</para>
    <para>The stock example of a place structure is that of the gismu 
    <quote>klama</quote>:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       klama: x1 comes/goes to destination x2 from origin x3 via route x4
            employing means of transport x5.
</programlisting>
    <para>The 
    <quote>x1 ... x5</quote>indicates that 
    <quote>klama</quote>is a five-place predicate, and show the natural order (as assigned by the language engineers) of those places: agent, destination, origin, route, means.</para>
    <para>The place structures of brivla are not absolutely stable aspects of the language. The work done so far has attempted to establish a basic place structure on which all users can, at first, agree. In the light of actual experience with the individual selbri of the language, there will inevitably be some degree of change to the brivla place structures.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section2">
    <title>Standard bridi form: 
    <quote>cu</quote></title>
    <para>The following cmavo is discussed in this section:</para>
    <cmavo-list>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>cu</cmavo>
        <selmaho>CU</selmaho>
        <description>prefixed selbri separator</description>
<!-- ^^   selbri separator, 492 -->
<indexterm><primary>selbri separator</primary></indexterm>
      </cmavo-entry>
    </cmavo-list>
    <para>The most usual way of constructing a bridi from a selbri such as 
    <quote>klama</quote>and an appropriate number of sumti is to place the sumti intended for the x1 place before the selbri, and all the other sumti in order after the selbri, thus:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-Ji94">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e2d1" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section2-example1" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi cu klama la bastn. la .atlantas. le dargu le karce</jbo>
        <en>I go to-Boston from-Atlanta via-the road using-the car.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Here the sumti are assigned to the places as follows:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       x1  agent         mi
       x2  destination   la bastn.
       x3  origin        la .atlantas.
       x4  route         le dargu
       x5  means         le karce
</programlisting>
    <para>(Note: Many of the examples in the rest of this chapter will turn out to have the same meaning as 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section2-example1" />; this fact will not be reiterated.)</para>
    <para>This ordering, with the x1 place before the selbri and all other places in natural order after the selbri, is called 
    <quote>standard bridi form</quote>, and is found in the bulk of Lojban bridi, whether used in main sentences or in subordinate clauses. However, many other forms are possible, such as:</para>
<!-- ^^   subordinate clauses: tense usage rules in English, 237 -->
<indexterm><primary>subordinate clauses</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   standard bridi form: definition, 188 -->
<indexterm><primary>standard bridi form</primary></indexterm>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-yLqT">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e2d2" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section2-example2" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi la bastn. la .atlantas. le dargu le karce cu klama</jbo>
        <en>I, to-Boston from-Atlanta via-the road using-the car, go.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Here the selbri is at the end; all the sumti are placed before it. However, the same order is maintained.</para>
    <para>Similarly, we may split up the sumti, putting some before the selbri and others after it:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-vzNY">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e2d3" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section2-example3" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi la bastn. cu klama la .atlantas. le dargu le karce</jbo>
        <en>I to-Boston go from-Atlanta via-the road using-the car.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>All of the variant forms in this section and following sections can be used to place emphasis on the part or parts which have been moved out of their standard places. Thus, 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section2-example2" />places emphasis on the selbri (because it is at the end); 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section2-example3" />emphasizes 
    <quote>la bastn.</quote>, because it has been moved before the selbri. Moving more than one component may dilute this emphasis. It is permitted, but no stylistic significance has yet been established for drastic reordering.</para>
    <para>In all these examples, the cmavo 
    <quote>cu</quote>(belonging to selma'o CU) is used to separate the selbri from any preceding sumti. It is never absolutely necessary to use 
    <quote>cu</quote>. However, providing it helps the reader or listener to locate the selbri quickly, and may make it possible to place a complex sumti just before the selbri, allowing the speaker to omit elidable terminators, possibly a whole stream of them, that would otherwise be necessary.</para>
<!-- ^^   elidable terminators: list, 486 -->
<indexterm><primary>elidable terminators</primary></indexterm>
    <para>The general rule, then, is that the selbri may occur anywhere in the bridi as long as the sumti maintain their order. The only exception (and it is an important one) is that if the selbri appears first, the x1 sumti is taken to have been omitted:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-aQtM">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e2d4" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section2-example4" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>klama la bastn. la .atlantas. le dargu le karce</jbo>
        <gloss>A-goer to-Boston from-Atlanta via-the road using-the car.</gloss>
        <gloss>Goes to-Boston from-Atlanta via-the road using-the car.</gloss>
        <en>Look: a goer to Boston from Atlanta via the road using the car!</en>
<!-- ^^   Boston from Atlanta: example, 187 -->
<indexterm><primary>Boston from Atlanta</primary></indexterm>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Here the x1 place is empty: the listener must guess from context who is going to Boston. In 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section2-example4" />, 
    <quote>klama</quote>is glossed 
    <quote>a goer</quote>rather than 
    <quote>go</quote>because 
    <quote>Go</quote>at the beginning of an English sentence would suggest a command: 
    <quote>Go to Boston!</quote>. 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section2-example4" />is not a command, simply a normal statement with the x1 place unspecified, causing the emphasis to fall on the selbri 
    <quote>klama</quote>. Such a bridi, with empty x1, is called an 
    <quote>observative</quote>, because it usually calls on the listener to observe something in the environment which would belong in the x1 place. The third translation above shows this observative nature. Sometimes it is the relationship itself which the listener is asked to observe.</para>
<!-- ^^   observative: contrasted with observation evidential, 316; definition, 188 -->
<indexterm><primary>observative</primary></indexterm>
    <para>(There is a way to both provide a sumti for the x1 place and put the selbri first in the bridi: see 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section3-example7" />.)</para>
    <para>Suppose the speaker desires to omit a place other than the x1 place? (Presumably it is obvious or, for one reason or another, not worth saying.) Places at the end may simply be dropped:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-5Eqa">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e2d5" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section2-example5" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi klama la bastn. la .atlantas.</jbo>
        <en>I go to-Boston from-Atlanta (via an unspecified route, using an unspecified means).</en>
<!-- ^^   unspecified route: example, 189 -->
<indexterm><primary>unspecified route</primary></indexterm>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section2-example5" />has empty x4 and x5 places: the speaker does not specify the route or the means of transport. However, simple omission will not work for a place when the places around it are to be specified: in</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-jh7T">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e2d6" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section2-example6" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi klama la bastn. la .atlantas. le karce</jbo>
        <en>I go to-Boston from-Atlanta via-the car.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>
    <quote>le karce</quote>occupies the x4 place, and therefore 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section2-example6" />means:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       I go to Boston from Atlanta, using the car as a route.
<!-- ^^   go to Boston from Atlanta: example, 187 -->
<indexterm><primary>go to Boston from Atlanta</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   Boston from Atlanta: example, 187 -->
<indexterm><primary>Boston from Atlanta</primary></indexterm>
</programlisting>
    <para>This is nonsense, since a car cannot be a route. What the speaker presumably meant is expressed by:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-tqoQ">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e2d7" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section2-example7" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi klama la bastn. la .atlantas. zo'e le karce</jbo>
        <en>I go to-Boston from-Atlanta via-something-unspecified using-the car.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Here the sumti cmavo 
    <quote>zo'e</quote>is used to explicitly fill the x4 place; 
    <quote>zo'e</quote>means 
    <quote>the unspecified thing</quote>and has the same meaning as leaving the place empty: the listener must infer the correct meaning from context.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section3">
    <title>Tagging places: FA</title>
    <para>The following cmavo are discussed in this section:</para>
    <cmavo-list>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>fa</cmavo>
        <selmaho>FA</selmaho>
        <description>tags x1 place</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>fe</cmavo>
        <selmaho>FA</selmaho>
        <description>tags x2 place</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>fi</cmavo>
        <selmaho>FA</selmaho>
        <description>tags x3 place</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>fo</cmavo>
        <selmaho>FA</selmaho>
        <description>tags x4 place</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>fu</cmavo>
        <selmaho>FA</selmaho>
        <description>tags x5 place</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>fi'a</cmavo>
<!-- ^^   fi'a, 191; effect on subsequent untagged sumti, 192 -->
<indexterm><primary>fi'a</primary></indexterm>
        <selmaho>FA</selmaho>
        <description>place structure question</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
    </cmavo-list>
    <para>In sentences like 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section2-example1" />, it is easy to get lost and forget which sumti falls in which place, especially if the sumti are more complicated than simple names or descriptions. The place structure tags of selma'o FA may be used to help clarify place structures. The five cmavo 
    <quote>fa</quote>, 
    <quote>fe</quote>, 
    <quote>fi</quote>, 
    <quote>fo</quote>, and 
    <quote>fu</quote>may be inserted just before the sumti in the x1 to x5 places respectively:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-yLop">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e3d1" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section3-example1" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>fa mi cu klama fe la bastn. fi la .atlantas. fo le dargu fu le karce</jbo>
        <gloss>x1= I go x2= Boston x3= Atlanta x4= the road x5= the car.</gloss>
        <en>I go to Boston from Atlanta via the road using the car.</en>
<!-- ^^   go to Boston from Atlanta: example, 187 -->
<indexterm><primary>go to Boston from Atlanta</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   Boston from Atlanta: example, 187 -->
<indexterm><primary>Boston from Atlanta</primary></indexterm>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>In 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section3-example1" />, the tag 
    <quote>fu</quote>before 
    <quote>le karce</quote>clarifies that 
    <quote>le karce</quote>occupies the x5 place of 
    <quote>klama</quote>. The use of 
    <quote>fu</quote>tells us nothing about the purpose or meaning of the x5 place; it simply says that 
    <quote>le karce</quote>occupies it.</para>
    <para>In 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section3-example1" />, the tags are overkill; they serve only to make 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section2-example1" />even longer than it is. Here is a better illustration of the use of FA tags for clarification:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-3CPJ">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e3d2" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section3-example2" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>fa mi klama fe le zdani be mi be'o poi nurma vau fi la nu,IORK.</jbo>
        <en>x1= I go x2= (the house of me) which is-rural x3= New York.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>In 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section3-example2" />, the place structure of 
    <quote>klama</quote>is as follows:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       x1  agent         mi
       x2  destination   le zdani be mi be'o poi nurma vau
       x3  origin        la nu,IORK.
       x4  route         (empty)
       x5  means         (empty)
</programlisting>
    <para>The 
    <quote>fi</quote>tag serves to remind the hearer that what follows is in the x3 place of 
    <quote>klama</quote>; after listening to the complex sumti occupying the x2 place, it's easy to get lost.</para>
    <para>Of course, once the sumti have been tagged, the order in which they are specified no longer carries the burden of distinguishing the places. Therefore, it is perfectly all right to scramble them into any order desired, and to move the selbri to anywhere in the bridi, even the beginning:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-YmN2">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e3d3" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section3-example3" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>klama fa mi fi la .atlantas. fu le karce fe la bastn. fo le dargu</jbo>
        <gloss>go x1= I x3= Atlanta x5= the car x2= Boston x4= the road.</gloss>
        <en>Go I from Atlanta using the car to Boston via the road.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Note that no 
    <quote>cu</quote>is permitted before the selbri in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section3-example3" />, because 
    <quote>cu</quote>separates the selbri from any preceding sumti, and 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section3-example3" />has no such sumti.</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-fG8R">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e3d4" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section3-example4" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>fu le karce fo le dargu fi la .atlantas. fe la bastn. cu klama fa mi</jbo>
        <gloss>x5= the car x4= the road x3= Atlanta x2= Boston go x1=I</gloss>
        <en>Using the car, via the road, from Atlanta to Boston go I.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section3-example4" />exhibits the reverse of the standard bridi form seen in 
<!-- ^^   standard bridi form: definition, 188 -->
<indexterm><primary>standard bridi form</primary></indexterm>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section2-example1" />and 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section3-example1" />, but still means exactly the same thing. If the FA tags were left out, however, producing:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-j7Nu">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e3d5" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section3-example5" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>le karce le dargu la .atlantas. la bastn. cu klama mi</jbo>
        <gloss>The car to-the road from-Atlanta via-Boston goes using-me.</gloss>
        <en>The car goes to the road from Atlanta, with Boston as the route, using me as a means of transport.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>the meaning would be wholly changed, and in fact nonsensical.</para>
    <para>Tagging places with FA cmavo makes it easy not only to reorder the places but also to omit undesirable ones, without any need for 
    <quote>zo'e</quote>or special rules about the x1 place:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-brGX">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e3d6" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section3-example6" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>klama fi la .atlantas. fe la bastn. fu le karce</jbo>
        <gloss>A-goer x3= Atlanta x2= Boston x5 = the car.</gloss>
        <en>A goer from Atlanta to Boston using the car.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Here the x1 and x4 places are empty, and so no sumti are tagged with 
    <quote>fa</quote>or 
    <quote>fo</quote>; in addition, the x2 and x3 places appear in reverse order.</para>
    <para>What if some sumti have FA tags and others do not? The rule is that after a FA-tagged sumti, any sumti following it occupy the places numerically succeeding it, subject to the proviso that an already-filled place is skipped:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-oDES">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e3d7" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section3-example7" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>klama fa mi la bastn. la .atlantas. le dargu le karce</jbo>
        <gloss>Go x1= I x2= Boston x3= Atlanta x4= the road x5= the car.</gloss>
        <en>Go I to Boston from Atlanta via the road using the car.</en>
<!-- ^^   Boston from Atlanta: example, 187 -->
<indexterm><primary>Boston from Atlanta</primary></indexterm>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>In 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section3-example7" />, the 
    <quote>fa</quote>causes 
    <quote>mi</quote>to occupy the x1 place, and then the following untagged sumti occupy in order the x2 through x5 places. This is the mechanism by which Lojban allows placing the selbri first while specifying a sumti for the x1 place.</para>
    <para>Here is a more complex (and more confusing) example:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-q8is">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e3d8" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section3-example8" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi klama fi la .atlantas. le dargu fe la bastn. le karce</jbo>
        <gloss>I go x3= Atlanta, the road x2= Boston, the car.</gloss>
        <en>I go from Atlanta via the road to Boston using the car.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>In 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section3-example8" />, 
    <quote>mi</quote>occupies the x1 place because it is the first sumti in the sentence (and is before the selbri). The second sumti, 
    <quote>la .atlantas.</quote>, occupies the x3 place by virtue of the tag 
<!-- ^^   virtue: example, 309 -->
<indexterm><primary>virtue</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>fi</quote>, and 
    <quote>le dargu</quote>occupies the x4 place as a result of following 
    <quote>la .atlantas.</quote>. Finally, 
    <quote>la bastn.</quote>occupies the x2 place because of its tag 
    <quote>fe</quote>, and 
    <quote>le karce</quote>skips over the already-occupied x3 and x4 places to land in the x5 place.</para>
    <para>Such a convoluted use of tags should probably be avoided except when trying for a literal translation of some English (or other natural-language) sentence; the rules stated here are merely given so that some standard interpretation is possible.</para>
    <para>It is grammatically permitted to tag more than one sumti with the same FA cmavo. The effect is that of making more than one claim:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-N1aE">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e3d9" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section3-example9" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>[fa] la rik. fa la djein. klama [fe] le skina fe le zdani fe le zarci</jbo>
        <en>[x1=] Rick x1= Jane goes-to x2= the movie x2= the house x2= the office</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>may be taken to say that both Rick and Jane go to the movie, the house, and the office, merging six claims into one. More likely, however, it will simply confuse the listener. There are better ways, involving logical connectives (explained in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter14" />), to say such things in Lojban. In fact, putting more than one sumti into a place is odd enough that it can only be done by explicit FA usage: this is the motivation for the proviso above, that already-occupied places are skipped. In this way, no sumti can be forced into a place already occupied unless it has an explicit FA cmavo tagging it.</para>
    <para>The cmavo 
    <quote>fi'a</quote>also belongs to selma'o FA, and allows Lojban users to ask questions about place structures. A bridi containing 
<!-- ^^   fi'a, 191; effect on subsequent untagged sumti, 192 -->
<indexterm><primary>fi'a</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>fi'a</quote>is a question, asking the listener to supply the appropriate other member of FA which will make the bridi a true statement:</para>
<!-- ^^   fi'a, 191; effect on subsequent untagged sumti, 192 -->
<indexterm><primary>fi'a</primary></indexterm>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-GnTu">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e3d10" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section3-example10" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>fi'a do dunda [fe] le vi rozgu</jbo>
<!-- ^^   fi'a, 191; effect on subsequent untagged sumti, 192 -->
<indexterm><primary>fi'a</primary></indexterm>
        <gloss>[what place]? you give x2= the nearby rose</gloss>
        <gloss>In what way are you involved in the giving of this rose?</gloss>
        <en>Are you the giver or the receiver of this rose?</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>In 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section3-example10" />, the speaker uses the selbri 
    <quote>dunda</quote>, whose place structure is:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       dunda: x1 gives x2 to x3
</programlisting>
    <para>The tagged sumti 
    <quote>fi'a do</quote>indicates that the speaker wishes to know whether the sumti 
<!-- ^^   fi'a, 191; effect on subsequent untagged sumti, 192 -->
<indexterm><primary>fi'a</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>do</quote>falls in the x1 or the x3 place (the x2 place is already occupied by 
    <quote>le rozgu</quote>). The listener can reply with a sentence consisting solely of a FA cmavo: 
    <quote>fa</quote>if the listener is the giver, 
    <quote>fi</quote>if he/she is the receiver.</para>
    <para>I have inserted the tag 
    <quote>fe</quote>in brackets into 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section3-example10" />, but it is actually not necessary, because 
    <quote>fi'a</quote>does not count as a numeric tag; therefore, 
<!-- ^^   fi'a, 191; effect on subsequent untagged sumti, 192 -->
<indexterm><primary>fi'a</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>le vi rozgu</quote>would necessarily be in the x2 place even if no tag were present, because it immediately follows the selbri.</para>
    <para>There is also another member of FA, namely 
    <quote>fai</quote>, which is discussed in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section12" />.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section4">
    <title>Conversion: SE</title>
    <para>The following cmavo are discussed in this section:</para>
    <cmavo-list>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>se</cmavo>
        <selmaho>SE</selmaho>
        <description>2nd place conversion</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>te</cmavo>
        <selmaho>SE</selmaho>
        <description>3rd place conversion</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>ve</cmavo>
        <selmaho>SE</selmaho>
        <description>4th place conversion</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>xe</cmavo>
        <selmaho>SE</selmaho>
        <description>5th place conversion</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
    </cmavo-list>
    <para>So far we have seen ways to move sumti around within a bridi, but the actual place structure of the selbri has always remained untouched. The conversion cmavo of selma'o SE are incorporated within the selbri itself, and produce a new selbri (called a converted selbri) with a different place structure. In particular, after the application of any SE cmavo, the number and purposes of the places remain the same, but two of them have been exchanged, the x1 place and another. Which place has been exchanged with x1 depends on the cmavo chosen. Thus, for example, when 
<!-- ^^   converted selbri: as different selbri from unconverted, 192; as resetting standard order, 193; compared with selbri with FA in meaning, 193; contrasted with other similar selbri, 193; contrasted with selbri with FA in structure, 193; definition, 192; forming with SE, 192; in descriptions, 193; place structure of, 192; retention of basic meaning in, 193; to access non-first place in description, 193 -->
<indexterm><primary>converted selbri</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>se</quote>is used, the x1 place is swapped with the x2 place.</para>
    <para>Note that the cmavo of SE begin with consecutive consonants in alphabetical order. There is no 
    <quote>1st place conversion</quote>cmavo, because exchanging the x1 place with itself is a pointless maneuver.</para>
    <para>Here are the place structures of 
    <quote>se klama</quote>:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       x1 is the destination of x2's going from x3 via x4 using x5
<!-- ^^   the destination: example, 193 -->
<indexterm><primary>the destination</primary></indexterm>
</programlisting>
    <para>and 
    <quote>te klama</quote>:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       x1 is the origin and x2 the destination of x3 going via x4 using x5
<!-- ^^   the destination: example, 193 -->
<indexterm><primary>the destination</primary></indexterm>
</programlisting>
    <para>and 
    <quote>ve klama</quote>:</para>
<!-- ^^   ve klama, 193; contrasted with pluta, 193 -->
<indexterm><primary>ve klama</primary></indexterm>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       x1 is the route to x2 from x3 used by x4 going via x5
</programlisting>
    <para>and 
    <quote>xe klama</quote>:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       x1 is the means in going to x2 from x3 via x4 employed by x5
</programlisting>
    <para>Note that the place structure numbers in each case continue to be listed in the usual order, x1 to x5.</para>
    <para>Consider the following pair of examples:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-1ce8">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e4d1" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section4-example1" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e4d2" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section4-example2" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>la bastn. cu se klama mi</jbo>
        <gloss>Boston is-the-destination of-me.</gloss>
        <gloss>Boston is my destination.</gloss>
        <en>Boston is gone to by me.</en>
        <jbo>fe la bastn. cu klama fa mi</jbo>
        <gloss>x2 = Boston go x1=I.</gloss>
        <en>To Boston go I.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section4-example1" />and 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section4-example2" />mean the same thing, in the sense that there is a relationship of going with the speaker as the agent and Boston as the destination (and with unspecified origin, route, and means). Structurally, however, they are quite different. 
<!-- ^^   the destination: example, 193 -->
<indexterm><primary>the destination</primary></indexterm>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section4-example1" />has 
    <quote>la bastn.</quote>in the x1 place and 
    <quote>mi</quote>in the x2 place of the selbri 
    <quote>se klama</quote>, and uses standard bridi order; 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section4-example2" />has 
    <quote>mi</quote>in the x1 place and 
    <quote>la bastn.</quote>in the x2 place of the selbri 
    <quote>klama</quote>, and uses a non-standard order.</para>
    <para>The most important use of conversion is in the construction of descriptions. A description is a sumti which begins with a cmavo of selma'o LA or LE, called the descriptor, and contains (in the simplest case) a selbri. We have already seen the descriptions 
    <quote>le dargu</quote>and 
    <quote>le karce</quote>. To this we could add:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-3YoA">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e4d3" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section4-example3" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>le klama</jbo>
        <en>the go-er, the one who goes</en>
<!-- ^^   the go-er: example, 193 -->
<indexterm><primary>the go-er</primary></indexterm>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>In every case, the description is about something which fits into the x1 place of the selbri. In order to get a description of a destination (that is, something fitting the x2 place of 
    <quote>klama</quote>), we must convert the selbri to 
    <quote>se klama</quote>, whose x1 place is a destination. The result is</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-brDN">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e4d4" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section4-example4" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>le se klama</jbo>
        <en>the destination gone to by someone</en>
<!-- ^^   the destination: example, 193 -->
<indexterm><primary>the destination</primary></indexterm>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Likewise, we can create three more converted descriptions:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-dKFA">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e4d5" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section4-example5" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e4d6" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section4-example6" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e4d7" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section4-example7" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>le te klama</jbo>
        <en>the origin of someone's going</en>
        <jbo>le ve klama</jbo>
<!-- ^^   ve klama, 193; contrasted with pluta, 193 -->
<indexterm><primary>ve klama</primary></indexterm>
        <en>the route of someone's going</en>
        <jbo>le xe klama</jbo>
        <en>the means by which someone goes</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section4-example6" />does not mean 
    <quote>the route</quote>plain and simple: that is 
    <quote>le pluta</quote>, using a different selbri. It means a route that is used by someone for an act of 
<!-- ^^   pluta, 193; contrasted with ve klama, 193 -->
<!-- ^^   ve klama, 193; contrasted with pluta, 193 -->
<indexterm><primary>ve klama</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>pluta</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>klama</quote>; that is, a journey with origin and destination. A 
    <quote>road</quote>on Mars, on which no one has traveled or is ever likely to, may be called 
    <quote>le pluta</quote>, but it cannot be 
<!-- ^^   pluta, 193; contrasted with ve klama, 193 -->
<!-- ^^   ve klama, 193; contrasted with pluta, 193 -->
<indexterm><primary>ve klama</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>pluta</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>le ve klama</quote>, since there exists no one for whom it is 
<!-- ^^   ve klama, 193; contrasted with pluta, 193 -->
<indexterm><primary>ve klama</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>le ve klama be fo da</quote>(the route taken in an actual journey by someone [da]).</para>
<!-- ^^   ve klama, 193; contrasted with pluta, 193 -->
<indexterm><primary>ve klama</primary></indexterm>
    <para>When converting selbri that are more complex than a single brivla, it is important to realize that the scope of a SE cmavo is only the following brivla (or equivalent unit). In order to convert an entire tanru, it is necessary to enclose the tanru in 
<!-- ^^   converting: operand to operator, 500; operator to selbri, 502; quantifier to selbri, 500; selbri to operand, 501; selbri to operator, 501; sumti to operand, 500; sumti to tanru unit, 500 -->
<indexterm><primary>converting</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>ke ... ke'e</quote>brackets:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-wQbB">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e4d8" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section4-example8" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi se ke blanu zdani [ke'e] ti</jbo>
        <en>I [2nd conversion] blue house this-thing</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>The place structure of 
    <quote>blanu zdani</quote>(blue house) is the same as that of 
    <quote>zdani</quote>, by the rule given in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section1" />. The place structure of 
    <quote>zdani</quote>is:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       zdani: x1 is a house/nest/lair/den for inhabitant x2
</programlisting>
    <para>The place structure of 
    <quote>se ke blanu zdani [ke'e]</quote>is therefore:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       x1 is the inhabitant of the blue house (etc.) x2
</programlisting>
    <para>Consequently, 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section4-example8" />means:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       I am the inhabitant of the blue house which is this thing.
</programlisting>
    <para>Conversion applied to only part of a tanru has subtler effects which are explained in 
    <xref linkend="selbri" />.</para>
    <para>It is grammatical to convert a selbri more than once with SE; later (inner) conversions are applied before earlier (outer) ones. For example, the place structure of 
    <quote>se te klama</quote>is achieved by exchanging the x1 and x2 place of 
<!-- ^^   se te, 194 -->
<indexterm><primary>se te</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>te klama</quote>, producing:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       x1 is the destination and x2 is the origin of x3 going via x4 using x5
<!-- ^^   the destination: example, 193 -->
<indexterm><primary>the destination</primary></indexterm>
</programlisting>
    <para>On the other hand, 
    <quote>te se klama</quote>has a place structure derived from swapping the x1 and x3 places of 
    <quote>se klama</quote>:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       x1 is the origin of x2's going to x3 via x4 using x5
</programlisting>
    <para>which is quite different. However, multiple conversions like this are never necessary. Arbitrary scrambling of places can be achieved more easily and far more intelligibly with FA tags, and only a single conversion is ever needed in a description.</para>
    <para>(Although no one has made any real use of it, it is perhaps worth noting that compound conversions of the form 
    <quote>setese</quote>, where the first and third cmavo are the same, effectively swap the two given places while leaving the others, including x1, alone: 
<!-- ^^   setese, 194 -->
<indexterm><primary>setese</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>setese</quote>(or equivalently 
<!-- ^^   setese, 194 -->
<indexterm><primary>setese</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>tesete</quote>) swap the x2 and x3 places, whereas 
    <quote>texete</quote>(or 
    <quote>xetexe</quote>) swap the x3 and x5 places.)</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section5">
    <title>Modal places: FIhO, FEhU</title>
    <para>The following cmavo are discussed in this section:</para>
    <cmavo-list>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>fi'o</cmavo>
        <selmaho>FIhO</selmaho>
        <description>modal place prefix</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>fe'u</cmavo>
        <selmaho>FEhU</selmaho>
        <description>modal terminator</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
    </cmavo-list>
    <para>Sometimes the place structures engineered into Lojban are inadequate to meet the needs of actual speech. Consider the gismu 
    <quote>viska</quote>, whose place structure is:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       viska: x1 sees x2 under conditions x3
</programlisting>
    <para>Seeing is a threefold relationship, involving an agent (le viska), an object of sight (le se viska), and an environment that makes seeing possible (le te viska). Seeing is done with one or more eyes, of course; in general, the eyes belong to the entity in the x1 place.</para>
    <para>Suppose, however, that you are blind in one eye and are talking to someone who doesn't know that. You might want to say, 
    <quote>I see you with the left eye.</quote>There is no place in the place structure of 
    <quote>viska</quote>such as 
    <quote>with eye x4</quote>or the like. Lojban allows you to solve the problem by adding a new place, changing the relationship:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-BSAc">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e5d1" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section5-example1" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi viska do fi'o kanla [fe'u] le zunle</jbo>
        <gloss>I see you [modal] eye: the left-thing</gloss>
        <en>I see you with the left eye.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>The three-place relation 
    <quote>viska</quote>has now acquired a fourth place specifying the eye used for seeing. The combination of the cmavo 
    <quote>fi'o</quote>(of selma'o FIhO) followed by a selbri, in this case the gismu 
    <quote>kanla</quote>, forms a tag which is prefixed to the sumti filling the new place, namely 
    <quote>le zunle</quote>. The semantics of 
    <quote>fi'o kanla le zunle</quote>is that 
    <quote>le zunle</quote>fills the x1 place of 
    <quote>kanla</quote>, whose place structure is</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       kanla: x1 is an/the eye of body x2
</programlisting>
    <para>Thus 
    <quote>le zunle</quote>is an eye. The x2 place of 
    <quote>kanla</quote>is unspecified and must be inferred from the context. It is important to remember that even though 
    <quote>le zunle</quote>is placed following 
    <quote>fi'o kanla</quote>, semantically it belongs in the x1 place of 
    <quote>kanla</quote>. The selbri may be terminated with 
    <quote>fe'u</quote>(of selma'o FEhU), an elidable terminator which is rarely required unless a non-logical connective follows the tag (omitting 
    <quote>fe'u</quote>in that case would make the connective affect the selbri).</para>
    <para>The term for such an added place is a 
    <quote>modal place</quote>, as distinguished from the regular numbered places. (This use of the word 
    <quote>modal</quote>is specific to the Loglan Project, and does not agree with the standard uses in either logic or linguistics, but is now too entrenched to change easily.) The 
    <quote>fi'o</quote>construction marking a modal place is called a 
    <quote>modal tag</quote>, and the sumti which follows it a 
    <quote>modal sumti</quote>; the purely Lojban terms 
<!-- ^^   modal sumti: and FA marking, 195; as first place of modal tag selbri, 195; definition (see also seltcita sumti), 195; effect on place structure, 195; leaving vague, 201; position in bridi, 195; unspecified, 201 -->
<!-- ^^   seltcita sumti: definition (see also modal sumti), 195 -->
<indexterm><primary>seltcita sumti</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>modal sumti</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>sumti tcita</quote>and 
    <quote>seltcita sumti</quote>, respectively, are also commonly used. Modal sumti may be placed anywhere within the bridi, in any order; they have no effect whatever on the rules for assigning unmarked bridi to numbered places, and they may not be marked with FA cmavo.</para>
<!-- ^^   seltcita sumti: definition (see also modal sumti), 195 -->
<indexterm><primary>seltcita sumti</primary></indexterm>
    <para>Consider 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section5-example1" />again. Another way to view the situation is to consider the speaker's left eye as a tool, a tool for seeing. The relevant selbri then becomes 
    <quote>pilno</quote>, whose place structure is</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       pilno: x1 uses x2 as a tool for purpose x3
</programlisting>
    <para>and we can rewrite 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section5-example1" />as</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-Lu15">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e5d2" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section5-example2" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi viska do fi'o se pilno le zunle kanla</jbo>
        <gloss>I see you [modal] [conversion] use: the left eye.</gloss>
        <en>I see you using my left eye.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Here the selbri belonging to the modal is 
    <quote>se pilno</quote>. The conversion of 
    <quote>pilno</quote>is necessary in order to get the 
    <quote>tool</quote>place into x1, since only x1 can be the modal sumti. The 
<!-- ^^   modal sumti: and FA marking, 195; as first place of modal tag selbri, 195; definition (see also seltcita sumti), 195; effect on place structure, 195; leaving vague, 201; position in bridi, 195; unspecified, 201 -->
<!-- ^^   seltcita sumti: definition (see also modal sumti), 195 -->
<indexterm><primary>seltcita sumti</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>modal sumti</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>tool user</quote>place is the x2 of 
    <quote>se pilno</quote>(because it is the x1 of 
    <quote>pilno</quote>) and remains unspecified. The tag 
    <quote>fi'o pilno</quote>would mean 
    <quote>with tool user</quote>, leaving the tool unspecified.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section6">
    <title>Modal tags: BAI</title>
    <para>There are certain selbri which seem particularly useful in constructing modal tags. In particular, 
    <quote>pilno</quote>is one of them. The place structure of 
    <quote>pilno</quote>is:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       pilno: x1 uses x2 as a tool for purpose x3
</programlisting>
    <para>and almost any selbri which represents an action may need to specify a tool. Having to say 
    <quote>fi'o se pilno</quote>frequently would make many Lojban sentences unnecessarily verbose and clunky, so an abbreviation is provided in the language design: the compound cmavo 
    <quote>sepi'o</quote>.</para>
<!-- ^^   sepi'o, 195 -->
<indexterm><primary>sepi'o</primary></indexterm>
    <para>Here 
    <quote>se</quote>is used before a cmavo, namely 
    <quote>pi'o</quote>, rather than before a brivla. The meaning of this cmavo, which belongs to selma'o BAI, is exactly the same as that of 
<!-- ^^   pi'o, 195 -->
<indexterm><primary>pi'o</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>fi'o pilno fe'u</quote>. Since what we want is a tag based on 
    <quote>se pilno</quote>rather than 
    <quote>pilno</quote>- the tool, not the tool user - the grammar allows a BAI cmavo to be converted using a SE cmavo. 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section5-example2" />may therefore be rewritten as:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-N32m">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e6d1" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section6-example1" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi viska do sepi'o le zunle kanla</jbo>
<!-- ^^   sepi'o, 195 -->
<indexterm><primary>sepi'o</primary></indexterm>
        <gloss>I see you with-tool: the left eye</gloss>
        <en>I see you using my left eye.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>The compound cmavo 
    <quote>sepi'o</quote>is much shorter than 
<!-- ^^   sepi'o, 195 -->
<indexterm><primary>sepi'o</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>fi'o se pilno [fe'u]</quote>and can be thought of as a single word meaning 
    <quote>with-tool</quote>. The modal tag 
    <quote>pi'o</quote>, with no 
<!-- ^^   pi'o, 195 -->
<indexterm><primary>pi'o</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>se</quote>, similarly means 
    <quote>with-tool-user</quote>, probably a less useful concept. Nevertheless, the parallelism with the place structure of 
    <quote>pilno</quote>makes the additional syllable worthwhile.</para>
    <para>Some BAI cmavo make sense with as well as without a SE cmavo; for example, 
    <quote>ka'a</quote>, the BAI corresponding to the gismu 
<!-- ^^   ka'a, 196 -->
<indexterm><primary>ka'a</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>klama</quote>, has five usable forms corresponding to the five places of 
    <quote>klama</quote>respectively:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       ka'a        with-goer
<!-- ^^   ka'a, 196 -->
<indexterm><primary>ka'a</primary></indexterm>
       seka'a      with-destination
       teka'a      with-origin
       veka'a      with-route
       xeka'a      with-means-of-transport
</programlisting>
    <para>Any of these tags may be used to provide modal places for bridi, as in the following examples:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-r0QA">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e6d2" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section6-example2" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>la .eivn. cu vecnu loi flira cinta ka'a mi</jbo>
<!-- ^^   ka'a, 196 -->
<indexterm><primary>ka'a</primary></indexterm>
        <gloss>Avon sells a-mass-of face paint with-goer me.</gloss>
<!-- ^^   Avon: example, 196 -->
<indexterm><primary>Avon</primary></indexterm>
        <en>I am a traveling cosmetics salesperson for Avon.</en>
<!-- ^^   Avon: example, 196 -->
<indexterm><primary>Avon</primary></indexterm>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>( 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section6-example2" />may seem a bit strained, but it illustrates the way in which an existing selbri, 
    <quote>vecnu</quote>in this case, may have a place added to it which might otherwise seem utterly unrelated.)</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-sE2t">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e6d3" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section6-example3" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e6d4" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section6-example4" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e6d5" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section6-example5" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e6d6" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section6-example6" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi cadzu seka'a la bratfyd.</jbo>
        <gloss>I walk with-destination Bradford.</gloss>
        <en>I am walking to Bradford.</en>
        <jbo>bloti teka'a la nu,IORK.</jbo>
        <gloss>[Observative:] is-a-boat with-origin New York</gloss>
        <en>A boat from New York!</en>
        <jbo>do bajra veka'a lo djine</jbo>
        <gloss>You run with-route a circle.</gloss>
        <en>You are running in circles.</en>
        <jbo>mi citka xeka'a le vinji</jbo>
        <gloss>I eat with-means-of-transport the airplane.</gloss>
        <en>I eat in the airplane.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>There are sixty-odd cmavo of selma'o BAI, based on selected gismu that seemed useful in a variety of settings. The list is somewhat biased toward English, because many of the cmavo were selected on the basis of corresponding English prepositions and preposition compounds such as 
<!-- ^^   prepositions: cmavo as Lojban equivalents, 50 -->
<indexterm><primary>prepositions</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   English prepositions: contrasted with modal tags in preciseness, 196 -->
<!-- ^^   prepositions: cmavo as Lojban equivalents, 50 -->
<indexterm><primary>prepositions</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>English prepositions</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   prepositions: cmavo as Lojban equivalents, 50 -->
<indexterm><primary>prepositions</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   basis: example, 317 -->
<indexterm><primary>basis</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>with</quote>, 
    <quote>without</quote>, and 
    <quote>by means of</quote>. The BAI cmavo, however, are far more precise than English prepositions, because their meanings are fixed by the place structures of the corresponding gismu.</para>
<!-- ^^   prepositions: cmavo as Lojban equivalents, 50 -->
<indexterm><primary>prepositions</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   English prepositions: contrasted with modal tags in preciseness, 196 -->
<!-- ^^   prepositions: cmavo as Lojban equivalents, 50 -->
<indexterm><primary>prepositions</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>English prepositions</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   prepositions: cmavo as Lojban equivalents, 50 -->
<indexterm><primary>prepositions</primary></indexterm>
    <para>All BAI cmavo have the form CV'V or CVV. Most of them are CV'V, where the C is the first consonant of the corresponding gismu and the two Vs are the two vowels of the gismu. The table in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section16" />shows the exceptions.</para>
    <para>There is one additional BAI cmavo that is not derived from a gismu: 
    <quote>do'e</quote>. This cmavo is used when an extra place is needed, but it seems useful to be vague about the semantic implications of the extra place:</para>
<!-- ^^   do'e, 197; compared with English of, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>do'e</primary></indexterm>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-2vMd">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e6d7" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section6-example7" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>lo nanmu be do'e le berti cu klama le tcadu</jbo>
<!-- ^^   do'e, 197; compared with English of, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>do'e</primary></indexterm>
        <gloss>Some man [related to] the north came to-the city.</gloss>
        <en>A man of the north came to the city.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Here 
    <quote>le berti</quote>is provided as a modal place of the selbri 
    <quote>nanmu</quote>, but its exact significance is vague, and is paralleled in the colloquial translation by the vague English preposition 
    <quote>of</quote>. 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section6-example7" />also illustrates a modal place bound into a selbri with 
    <quote>be</quote>. This construction is useful when the selbri of a description requires a modal place; this and other uses of 
    <quote>be</quote>are more fully explained in 
    <xref linkend="selbri" />.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section7">
    <title>Modal sentence connection: the causals</title>
<!-- ^^   causals: claiming the relation contrasted with claiming cause and/or effect and/or relation, 198; gismu, 197; modal, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>causals</primary></indexterm>
    <para>The following cmavo are discussed in this section:</para>
    <cmavo-list>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>ri'a</cmavo>
        <selmaho>BAI</selmaho>
        <description>rinka modal: physical cause</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>ki'u</cmavo>
<!-- ^^   ki'u, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>ki'u</primary></indexterm>
        <selmaho>BAI</selmaho>
        <description>krinu modal: justification</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>mu'i</cmavo>
<!-- ^^   mu'i, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>mu'i</primary></indexterm>
        <selmaho>BAI</selmaho>
        <description>mukti modal: motivation</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>ni'i</cmavo>
<!-- ^^   ni'i, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>ni'i</primary></indexterm>
        <selmaho>BAI</selmaho>
        <description>nibli modal: logical entailment</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
    </cmavo-list>
    <para>This section has two purposes. On the one hand, it explains the grammatical construct called 
    <quote>modal sentence connection</quote>. On the other, it exemplifies some of the more useful BAI cmavo: the causals. (There are other BAI cmavo which have causal implications: 
<!-- ^^   modal sentence connection, 198; condensing, 200; effect on modal, 199; forethought, 199; relation to modal of first sentence in, 199; relation to modal of second sentence in, 199; table of equivalent schemata, 249; with other than causals, 199 -->
<indexterm><primary>modal sentence connection</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   causals: claiming the relation contrasted with claiming cause and/or effect and/or relation, 198; gismu, 197; modal, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>causals</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>ja'e</quote>means 
    <quote>with result</quote>, and so 
    <quote>seja'e</quote>means 
    <quote>with cause of unspecified nature</quote>; likewise, 
    <quote>gau</quote>means 
    <quote>with agent</quote>and 
    <quote>tezu'e</quote>means 
    <quote>with purpose</quote>. These other modal cmavo will not be further discussed here, as my purpose is to explain modal sentence connection rather than Lojbanic views of causation.)</para>
<!-- ^^   modal sentence connection, 198; condensing, 200; effect on modal, 199; forethought, 199; relation to modal of first sentence in, 199; relation to modal of second sentence in, 199; table of equivalent schemata, 249; with other than causals, 199 -->
<indexterm><primary>modal sentence connection</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   modal cmavo: basis in gismu place structure, 210; list of irregular derivation, 209; position relative to selbri, 104; regular form for derivation, 208; table with English equivalents, 210 -->
<indexterm><primary>modal cmavo</primary></indexterm>
    <para>There are four causal gismu in Lojban, distinguishing different versions of the relationships lumped in English as 
    <quote>causal</quote>:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       rinka: event x1 physically causes event x2
       krinu: event x1 is the justification for event x2
       mukti: event x1 is the (human) motive for event x2
       nibli: event x1 logically entails event x2
</programlisting>
    <para>Each of these gismu has a related modal: 
    <quote>ri'a</quote>, 
    <quote>ki'u</quote>, 
<!-- ^^   ki'u, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>ki'u</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>mu'i</quote>, and 
<!-- ^^   mu'i, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>mu'i</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>ni'i</quote>respectively. Using these gismu and these modals, we can create various causal sentences with different implications:</para>
<!-- ^^   ni'i, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>ni'i</primary></indexterm>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-RGdy">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e7d1" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section7-example1" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e7d2" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section7-example2" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e7d3" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section7-example3" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e7d4" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section7-example4" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>le spati cu banro ri'a le nu do djacu dunda fi le spati</jbo>
        <gloss>The plant grows with-physical-cause the event-of you water give to the plant.</gloss>
        <en>The plant grows because you water it.</en>
        <jbo>la djan. cpacu le pamoi se jinga ki'u le nu la djan. jinga</jbo>
<!-- ^^   ki'u, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>ki'u</primary></indexterm>
        <gloss>John gets the first prize with-justification the event-of John wins.</gloss>
        <en>John got the first prize because he won.</en>
        <jbo>mi lebna le cukta mu'i le nu mi viska le cukta</jbo>
<!-- ^^   mu'i, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>mu'i</primary></indexterm>
        <gloss>I took the book with-motivation the event-of I saw the book.</gloss>
        <en>I took the book because I saw it.</en>
        <jbo>la sokrates. morsi binxo ni'i le nu la sokrates. remna</jbo>
<!-- ^^   ni'i, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>ni'i</primary></indexterm>
        <gloss>Socrates dead-became with-logical-justification Socrates is-human.</gloss>
<!-- ^^   Socrates: example, 198 -->
<indexterm><primary>Socrates</primary></indexterm>
        <en>Socrates died because Socrates is human.</en>
<!-- ^^   Socrates: example, 198 -->
<indexterm><primary>Socrates</primary></indexterm>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>In 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section7-example1" />through 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section7-example4" />, the same English word 
    <quote>because</quote>is used to translate all four modals, but the types of cause being expressed are quite different. Let us now focus on 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section7-example1" />, and explore some variations on it.</para>
    <para>As written, 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section7-example1" />claims that the plant grows, but only refers to the event of watering it in an abstraction bridi (abstractions are explained in 
<!-- ^^   abstraction bridi: contrasted with component non-abstraction bridi in meaning, 98; effect on claim of bridi, 198 -->
<indexterm><primary>abstraction bridi</primary></indexterm>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter11" />) without actually making a claim. If I express 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section7-example1" />, I have said that the plant in fact grows, but I have not said that you actually water it, merely that there is a causal relationship between watering and growing. This is semantically asymmetrical. Suppose I wanted to claim that the plant was being watered, and only mention its growth as ancillary information? Then we could reverse the main bridi and the abstraction bridi, saying:</para>
<!-- ^^   abstraction bridi: contrasted with component non-abstraction bridi in meaning, 98; effect on claim of bridi, 198 -->
<indexterm><primary>abstraction bridi</primary></indexterm>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-ibro">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e7d5" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section7-example5" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>do djacu dunda fi le spati seri'a le nu ri banro</jbo>
        <gloss>You water-give to the plant with-physical-effect it grows.</gloss>
        <en>You water the plant; therefore, it grows.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>with the 
    <quote>ri'a</quote>changed to 
    <quote>seri'a</quote>. In addition, there are also symmetrical forms:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-1YHv">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e7d6" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section7-example6" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>le nu do djacu dunda fi le spati cu rinka</jbo>
        <gloss>le nu le spati cu banro</gloss>
        <gloss>The event-of (you water-give to the plant) causes</gloss>
        <gloss>the event-of (the plant grows).</gloss>
        <gloss>Your watering the plant causes its growth.</gloss>
        <en>If you water the plant, then it grows.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>does not claim either event, but asserts only the causal relationship between them. So in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section7-example6" />, I am not saying that the plant grows nor that you have in fact watered it. The second colloquial translation shows a form of 
    <quote>if-then</quote>in English quite distinct from the logical connective 
    <quote>if-then</quote>explained in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter14" />.</para>
    <para>Suppose we wish to claim both events as well as their causal relationship? We can use one of two methods:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-9VRd">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e7d7" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section7-example7" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e7d8" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section7-example8" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>le spati cu banro .iri'abo do djacu dunda fi le spati</jbo>
<!-- ^^   iri'abo, 198 -->
<indexterm><primary>iri'abo</primary></indexterm>
        <gloss>The plant grows. Because you water-give to the plant.</gloss>
        <en>The plant grows because you water it.</en>
        <jbo>do djacu dunda fi le spati .iseri'abo le spati cu banro</jbo>
        <gloss>You water-give to the plant. Therefore it grows.</gloss>
        <en>You water the plant; therefore, it grows.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>The compound cmavo 
    <quote>.iri'abo</quote>and 
<!-- ^^   iri'abo, 198 -->
<indexterm><primary>iri'abo</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>.iseri'abo</quote>serve to connect two bridi, as the initial 
    <quote>.i</quote>indicates. The final 
    <quote>bo</quote>is necessary to prevent the modal from 
    <quote>taking over</quote>the following sumti. If the 
    <quote>bo</quote>were omitted from 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section7-example7" />we would have:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-Wo6K">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e7d9" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section7-example9" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>le spati cu banro .i ri'a do djacu dunda fi le spati</jbo>
        <gloss>The plant grows. Because of you, [something] water-gives to the plant.</gloss>
        <en>The plant grows. Because of you, water is given to the plant.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Because 
    <quote>ri'a do</quote>is a modal sumti in 
<!-- ^^   modal sumti: and FA marking, 195; as first place of modal tag selbri, 195; definition (see also seltcita sumti), 195; effect on place structure, 195; leaving vague, 201; position in bridi, 195; unspecified, 201 -->
<!-- ^^   seltcita sumti: definition (see also modal sumti), 195 -->
<indexterm><primary>seltcita sumti</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>modal sumti</primary></indexterm>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section7-example9" />, there is no longer an explicit sumti in the x1 place of 
    <quote>djacu dunda</quote>, and the translation must be changed.</para>
    <para>The effect of sentences like 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section7-example7" />and 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section7-example8" />is that the modal, 
    <quote>ri'a</quote>in this example, no longer modifies an explicit sumti. Instead, the sumti is implicit, the event given by a full bridi. Furthermore, there is a second implication: that the first bridi fills the x2 place of the gismu 
    <quote>rinka</quote>; it specifies an event which is the effect. I am therefore claiming three things: that the plant grows, that you have watered it, and that there is a cause-and-effect relationship between the two.</para>
    <para>In principle, any modal tag can appear in a sentence connective of the type exemplified by 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section7-example7" />and 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section7-example8" />. However, it makes little sense to use any modals which do not expect events or other abstractions to fill the places of the corresponding gismu. The sentence connective 
    <quote>.ibaubo</quote>is perfectly grammatical, but it is hard to imagine any two sentences which could be connected by an 
    <quote>in-language</quote>modal. This is because a sentence describes an event, and an event can be a cause or an effect, but not a language.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section8">
    <title>Other modal connections</title>
    <para>Like many Lojban grammatical constructions, sentence modal connection has both forethought and afterthought forms. (See 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter14" />for a more detailed discussion of Lojban connectives.) 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section7" />exemplifies only afterthought modal connection, illustrated here by:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-2D4c">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e8d1" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section8-example1" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi jgari lei djacu .iri'abo mi jgari le kabri</jbo>
<!-- ^^   iri'abo, 198 -->
<indexterm><primary>iri'abo</primary></indexterm>
        <gloss>I grasp the-mass-of water with-physical-cause I grasp the cup.</gloss>
        <gloss>Causing the mass of water to be grasped by me, I grasped the cup.</gloss>
        <en>I grasp the water because I grasp the cup.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>An afterthought connection is one that is signaled only by a cmavo (or a compound cmavo, in this case) between the two constructs being connected. Forethought connection uses a signal both before the first construct and between the two: the use of 
<!-- ^^   afterthought connection: contrasted with forethought for grammatical utterances, 352; definition, 199; of operands, 453; of operators, 453 -->
<indexterm><primary>afterthought connection</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>both</quote>and 
    <quote>and</quote>in the first half of this sentence represents a forethought connection (though not a modal one).</para>
<!-- ^^   forethought connection: contrasted with afterthought for grammatical utterances, 352; definition, 199; in abstractions, 365; in tenses, 363; observatives, 347; of operands, 453; of operators, 453 -->
<!-- ^^   observatives: and abstractions, 255; quick-tour version, 15 -->
<indexterm><primary>observatives</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>forethought connection</primary></indexterm>
    <para>To make forethought modal sentence connections in Lojban, place the modal plus 
    <quote>gi</quote>before the first bridi, and 
    <quote>gi</quote>between the two. No 
    <quote>.i</quote>is used within the construct. The forethought equivalent of 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section8-example1" />is:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-d2b9">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e8d2" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section8-example2" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>ri'agi mi jgari le kabri gi mi jgari lei djacu</jbo>
        <gloss>With-physical-cause I grasp the cup, I grasp the-mass-of water.</gloss>
        <en>Because I grasp the cup, I grasp the water.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Note that the cause, the x1 of 
    <quote>rinka</quote>is now placed first. To keep the two bridi in the original order of 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section8-example1" />, we could say:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-rQ77">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e8d3" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section8-example3" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>seri'agi mi jgari lei djacu gi mi jgari le kabri</jbo>
        <en>With-physical-effect I grasp the-mass-of water, I grasp the cup.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>In English, the sentence 
    <quote>*Therefore I grasp the water, I grasp the cup</quote>is ungrammatical, because 
    <quote>therefore</quote>is not grammatically equivalent to 
    <quote>because</quote>. In Lojban, 
    <quote>seri'agi</quote>can be used just like 
    <quote>ri'agi</quote>.</para>
    <para>When the two bridi joined by a modal connection have one or more elements (selbri or sumti or both) in common, there are various condensed forms that can be used in place of full modal sentence connection with both bridi completely stated.</para>
<!-- ^^   modal sentence connection, 198; condensing, 200; effect on modal, 199; forethought, 199; relation to modal of first sentence in, 199; relation to modal of second sentence in, 199; table of equivalent schemata, 249; with other than causals, 199 -->
<indexterm><primary>modal sentence connection</primary></indexterm>
    <para>When the bridi are the same except for a single sumti, as in Examples 8.1 through 8.3, then a sumti modal connection may be employed:</para>
<!-- ^^   sumti modal connection, 200 -->
<indexterm><primary>sumti modal connection</primary></indexterm>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-o7FG">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e8d4" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section8-example4" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi jgari ri'agi le kabri gi lei djacu</jbo>
        <en>I grasp because the cup, the-mass-of water.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section8-example4" />means exactly the same as 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section8-example1" />through 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section8-example3" />, but there is no idiomatic English translation that will distinguish it from them.</para>
    <para>If the two connected bridi are different in more than one sumti, then a termset may be employed. Termsets are explained more fully in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter14" />, but are essentially a mechanism for creating connections between multiple sumti simultaneously.</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-LetE">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e8d5" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section8-example5" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi dunda le cukta la djan. .imu'ibo la djan. dunda lei jdini mi</jbo>
        <gloss>I gave the book to John. Motivated-by John gave the-mass-of money to-me.</gloss>
        <en>I gave the book to John, because John gave money to me.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>means the same as:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-tFSC">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e8d6" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section8-example6" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>nu'i mu'igi mi le cukta la djan. gi la djan. lei jdini mi nu'u dunda</jbo>
        <en>[start] because I, the book, John; John, the-mass-of money, me [end] gives.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Here there are three sumti in each half of the termset, because the two bridi share only their selbri.</para>
    <para>There is no modal connection between selbri as such: bridi which differ only in the selbri can be modally connected using bridi-tail modal connection. The bridi-tail construct is more fully explained in 
<!-- ^^   bridi-tail modal connection, 200 -->
<indexterm><primary>bridi-tail modal connection</primary></indexterm>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter14" />, but essentially it consists of a selbri with optional sumti following it. 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section7-example3" />is suitable for bridi-tail connection, and could be shortened to:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-Do9b">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e8d7" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section8-example7" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi mu'igi viska le cukta gi lebna le cukta</jbo>
        <en>I, because saw the book, took the book.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Again, no straightforward English translation exists. It is even possible to shorten 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section8-example7" />further to:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-YXps">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e8d8" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section8-example8" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi mu'igi viska gi lebna vau le cukta</jbo>
        <en>I because saw, therefore took, the book.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>where 
    <quote>le cukta</quote>is set off by the non-elidable 
    <quote>vau</quote>and is made to belong to both bridi-tails - see 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter14" />for more explanations.</para>
    <para>Since this is a chapter on rearranging sumti, it is worth pointing out that 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section8-example8" />can be further rearranged to:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-Pxca">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e8d9" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section8-example9" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi le cukta mu'igi viska gi lebna</jbo>
        <en>I, the book, because saw, therefore took.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>which doesn't require the extra 
    <quote>vau</quote>; all sumti before a conjunction of bridi-tails are shared.</para>
    <para>Finally, mathematical operands can be modally connected.</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-J2T5">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e8d10" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section8-example10" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>li ny. du li vo</jbo>
        <gloss>.ini'ibo li ny. du li re su'i re</gloss>
        <en>the number</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>can be reduced to:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-Mfe4">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e8d11" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section8-example11" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>li ny. du li ni'igi vei re su'i re [ve'o] gi vo</jbo>
        <en>the-number</en>
        <jbo>= the-number because ( 2 + 2 ) therefore 4.</jbo>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>The cmavo 
    <quote>vei</quote>and 
    <quote>ve'o</quote>represent mathematical parentheses, and are required so that 
    <quote>ni'igi</quote>affects more than just the immediately following operand, namely the first 
    <quote>re</quote>. (The right parenthesis, 
    <quote>ve'o</quote>, is an elidable terminator.) As usual, no English translation does 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section8-example11" />justice.</para>
    <para>Note: Due to restrictions on the Lojban parsing algorithm, it is not possible to form modal connectives using the 
<!-- ^^   modal connectives: fi'o prohibited in, 201 -->
<indexterm><primary>modal connectives</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>fi'o</quote>-plus-selbri form of modal. Only the predefined modals of selma'o BAI can be compounded as shown in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section7" />and 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section8" />.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section9">
    <title>Modal selbri</title>
    <para>Consider the example:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-bT4c">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e9d1" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section9-example1" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi tavla bau la lojban. bai tu'a la frank.</jbo>
        <gloss>I speak in-language Lojban with-compeller some-act-by Frank.</gloss>
        <en>I speak in Lojban, under compulsion by Frank.</en>
<!-- ^^   under compulsion: example, 201 -->
<indexterm><primary>under compulsion</primary></indexterm>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section9-example1" />has two modal sumti, using the modals 
<!-- ^^   modal sumti: and FA marking, 195; as first place of modal tag selbri, 195; definition (see also seltcita sumti), 195; effect on place structure, 195; leaving vague, 201; position in bridi, 195; unspecified, 201 -->
<!-- ^^   seltcita sumti: definition (see also modal sumti), 195 -->
<indexterm><primary>seltcita sumti</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>modal sumti</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>bau</quote>and 
    <quote>bai</quote>. Suppose we wanted to specify the language explicitly but be vague about who's doing the compelling. We can simplify 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section9-example1" />to:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-dbSy">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e9d2" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section9-example2" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi tavla bau la lojban. bai [ku].</jbo>
        <en>I speak in-language Lojban under-compulsion.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>In 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section9-example2" />, the elidable terminator 
    <quote>ku</quote>has taken the place of the sumti which would normally follow 
    <quote>bai</quote>. Alternatively, we could specify the one who compels but keep the language vague:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-Qc8w">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e9d3" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section9-example3" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi tavla bau [ku] bai tu'a la frank.</jbo>
        <en>I speak in-some-language under-compulsion-by some-act-by Frank.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>We are also free to move the modal-plus- 
    <quote>ku</quote>around the bridi:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-2utY">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e9d4" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section9-example4" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>bau [ku] bai ku mi tavla</jbo>
        <en>In-some-language under-compulsion I speak.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>An alternative to using 
    <quote>ku</quote>is to place the modal cmavo right before the selbri, following the 
<!-- ^^   modal cmavo: basis in gismu place structure, 210; list of irregular derivation, 209; position relative to selbri, 104; regular form for derivation, 208; table with English equivalents, 210 -->
<indexterm><primary>modal cmavo</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>cu</quote>which often appears there. When a modal is present, the 
    <quote>cu</quote>is almost never necessary.</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-613h">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e9d5" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section9-example5" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi bai tavla bau la lojban.</jbo>
        <en>I compelledly speak in-language Lojban.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>In this use, the modal is like a tanru modifier semantically, although grammatically it is quite distinct. 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section9-example5" />is very similar in meaning to:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-pVUT">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e9d6" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section9-example6" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi se bapli tavla bau la lojban.</jbo>
        <en>I compelledly-speak in-language Lojban.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>The 
    <quote>se</quote>conversion is needed because 
    <quote>bapli tavla</quote>would be a 
    <quote>compeller type of speaker</quote>rather than a 
    <quote>compelled (by someone) type of speaker</quote>, which is what a 
    <quote>bai tavla</quote>is.</para>
    <para>If the modal preceding a selbri is constructed using 
    <quote>fi'o</quote>, then 
    <quote>fe'u</quote>is required to prevent the main selbri and the modal selbri from colliding:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-SfwV">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e9d7" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section9-example7" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi fi'o kanla fe'u viska do</jbo>
        <gloss>I with-eye see you.</gloss>
        <en>I see you with my eye(s).</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>There are two other uses of modals. A modal can be attached to a pair of bridi-tails that have already been connected by a logical, non-logical, or modal connection (see 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter14" />for more on logical and non-logical connections):</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-vCzL">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e9d8" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section9-example8" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi bai ke ge klama le zarci gi cadzu le bisli [ke'e]</jbo>
<!-- ^^   bai ke, 202 -->
<indexterm><primary>bai ke</primary></indexterm>
        <gloss>I under-compulsion (both go to-the market and walk on-the ice).</gloss>
        <en>Under compulsion, I both go to the market and walk on the ice.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Here the 
    <quote>bai</quote>is spread over both 
    <quote>klama le zarci</quote>and 
    <quote>cadzu le bisli</quote>, and the 
    <quote>ge ... gi</quote>represents the logical connection 
    <quote>both-and</quote>between the two.</para>
    <para>Similarly, a modal can be attached to multiple sentences that have been combined with 
    <quote>tu'e</quote>and 
    <quote>tu'u</quote>, which are explained in more detail in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter19" />:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-boYr">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e9d9" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section9-example9" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>bai tu'e mi klama le zarci .i mi cadzu le bisli [tu'u]</jbo>
        <en>Under-compulsion [start] I go to-the market. I walk on-the ice [end].</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>means the same thing as 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section9-example8" />.</para>
    <para>Note: Either BAI modals or 
    <quote>fi'o</quote>-plus-selbri modals may correctly be used in any of the constructions discussed in this section.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section10">
    <title>Modal relative phrases; Comparison</title>
    <para>The following cmavo are discussed in this section:</para>
    <cmavo-list>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>pe</cmavo>
        <selmaho>GOI</selmaho>
        <description>restrictive relative phrase</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>ne</cmavo>
        <selmaho>GOI</selmaho>
        <description>incidental relative phrase</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>mau</cmavo>
<!-- ^^   mau, 203, 432; avoiding in favor of seme'a, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>mau</primary></indexterm>
        <selmaho>BAI</selmaho>
        <description>zmadu modal</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>me'a</cmavo>
<!-- ^^   me'a, 203; avoiding in favor of semau, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>me'a</primary></indexterm>
        <selmaho>BAI</selmaho>
        <description>mleca modal</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
    </cmavo-list>
    <para>Relative phrases and clauses are explained in much more detail in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter8" />. However, there is a construction which combines a modal with a relative phrase which is relevant to this chapter. Consider the following examples of relative clauses:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-vuYy">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e10d1" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section10-example1" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e10d2" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section10-example2" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>la .apasionatas. poi se cusku la .artr. rubnstain. cu se nelci mi</jbo>
        <en>The Appassionata which is-expressed-by Arthur Rubinstein is-liked-by me.</en>
<!-- ^^   Appassionata: example, 202 -->
<indexterm><primary>Appassionata</primary></indexterm>
        <jbo>la .apasionatas. noi se finti la betovn. cu se nelci mi</jbo>
        <en>The Appassionata, which is-created-by Beethoven, is-liked-by me.</en>
<!-- ^^   Beethoven: example, 202 -->
<indexterm><primary>Beethoven</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   Appassionata: example, 202 -->
<indexterm><primary>Appassionata</primary></indexterm>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>In 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example1" />, 
    <quote>la .apasionatas.</quote>refers to a particular performance of the sonata, namely the one performed by Rubinstein. Therefore, the relative clause 
    <quote>poi se cusku</quote>uses the cmavo 
    <quote>poi</quote>(of selma'o NOI) to restrict the meaning of 
    <quote>la .apasionatas</quote>to the performance in question.</para>
    <para>In 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example2" />, however, 
    <quote>la .apasionatas.</quote>refers to the sonata as a whole, and the information that it was composed by Beethoven is merely incidental. The cmavo 
<!-- ^^   Beethoven: example, 202 -->
<indexterm><primary>Beethoven</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>noi</quote>(also of selma'o NOI) expresses the incidental nature of this relationship.</para>
    <para>The cmavo 
    <quote>pe</quote>and 
    <quote>ne</quote>(of selma'o GOI) are roughly equivalent to 
    <quote>poi</quote>and 
    <quote>noi</quote>respectively, but are followed by sumti rather than full bridi. We can abbreviate 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example1" />and 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example2" />to:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-JtC7">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e10d3" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section10-example3" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e10d4" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section10-example4" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>la .apasionatas pe la .artr. rubnstain. se nelci mi</jbo>
        <en>The Appassionata of Arthur Rubinstein is-liked-by me.</en>
<!-- ^^   Appassionata: example, 202 -->
<indexterm><primary>Appassionata</primary></indexterm>
        <jbo>la .apasionatas ne la betovn. se nelci mi</jbo>
        <en>The Appassionata, which is of Beethoven, is-liked-by me.</en>
<!-- ^^   Beethoven: example, 202 -->
<indexterm><primary>Beethoven</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   Appassionata: example, 202 -->
<indexterm><primary>Appassionata</primary></indexterm>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Here the precise selbri of the relative clauses is lost: all we can tell is that the Appassionata is connected in some way with Rubinstein (in 
<!-- ^^   Appassionata: example, 202 -->
<indexterm><primary>Appassionata</primary></indexterm>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example3" />) and Beethoven (in 
<!-- ^^   Beethoven: example, 202 -->
<indexterm><primary>Beethoven</primary></indexterm>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example4" />), and that the relationships are respectively restrictive and incidental.</para>
    <para>It happens that both 
    <quote>cusku</quote>and 
    <quote>finti</quote>have BAI cmavo, namely 
    <quote>cu'u</quote>and 
<!-- ^^   cu'u, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>cu'u</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>fi'e</quote>. We can recast 
<!-- ^^   fi'e, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>fi'e</primary></indexterm>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example3" />and 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example4" />as:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-oIoY">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e10d5" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section10-example5" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e10d6" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section10-example6" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>la .apasionatas pe cu'u la .artr. rubnstain. cu se nelci mi</jbo>
<!-- ^^   cu'u, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>cu'u</primary></indexterm>
        <en>The Appassionata expressed-by Arthur Rubinstein is-liked-by me.</en>
<!-- ^^   Appassionata: example, 202 -->
<indexterm><primary>Appassionata</primary></indexterm>
        <jbo>la .apasionatas ne fi'e la betovn. cu se nelci mi</jbo>
<!-- ^^   fi'e, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>fi'e</primary></indexterm>
        <en>The Appassionata, invented-by Beethoven, is-liked-by me.</en>
<!-- ^^   Beethoven: example, 202 -->
<indexterm><primary>Beethoven</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   Appassionata: example, 202 -->
<indexterm><primary>Appassionata</primary></indexterm>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example5" />and 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example6" />have the full semantic content of 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example1" />and 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example2" />respectively.</para>
    <para>Modal relative phrases are often used with the BAI cmavo 
    <quote>mau</quote>and 
<!-- ^^   mau, 203, 432; avoiding in favor of seme'a, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>mau</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>me'a</quote>, which are based on the comparative gismu 
<!-- ^^   me'a, 203; avoiding in favor of semau, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>me'a</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>zmadu</quote>(more than) and 
    <quote>mleca</quote>(less than) respectively. The place structures are:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       zmadu: x1 is more than x2 in property/quantity x3 by amount x4
       mleca: x1 is less than x2 in property/quantity x3 by amount x4
</programlisting>
    <para>Here are some examples:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-Jr4V">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e10d7" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section10-example7" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>la frank. nelci la betis. ne semau la meiris.</jbo>
        <gloss>Frank likes Betty, which-is more-than Mary.</gloss>
        <en>Frank likes Betty more than (he likes) Mary.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example7" />requires that Frank likes Betty, but adds the information that his liking for Betty exceeds his liking for Mary. The modal appears in the form 
    <quote>semau</quote>because the x2 place of 
    <quote>zmadu</quote>is the basis for comparison: in this case, Frank's liking for Mary.</para>
<!-- ^^   comparison: claims related to based on form, 204 -->
<indexterm><primary>comparison</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   basis: example, 317 -->
<indexterm><primary>basis</primary></indexterm>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-ecf1">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e10d8" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section10-example8" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>la frank. nelci la meiris. ne seme'a la betis.</jbo>
        <gloss>Frank likes Mary, which-is less-than Betty.</gloss>
        <en>Frank likes Mary less than (he likes) Betty.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Here we are told that Frank likes Mary less than he likes Betty; the information about the comparison is the same. It would be possible to rephrase 
<!-- ^^   comparison: claims related to based on form, 204 -->
<indexterm><primary>comparison</primary></indexterm>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example7" />using 
    <quote>me'a</quote>rather than 
<!-- ^^   me'a, 203; avoiding in favor of semau, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>me'a</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>semau</quote>, and 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example8" />using 
    <quote>mau</quote>rather than 
<!-- ^^   mau, 203, 432; avoiding in favor of seme'a, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>mau</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>seme'a</quote>, but such usage would be unnecessarily confusing. Like many BAI cmavo, 
    <quote>mau</quote>and 
<!-- ^^   mau, 203, 432; avoiding in favor of seme'a, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>mau</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>me'a</quote>are more useful when converted with 
<!-- ^^   me'a, 203; avoiding in favor of semau, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>me'a</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>se</quote>.</para>
    <para>If the 
    <quote>ne</quote>were omitted in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example7" />and 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example8" />, the modal sumti ( 
<!-- ^^   modal sumti: and FA marking, 195; as first place of modal tag selbri, 195; definition (see also seltcita sumti), 195; effect on place structure, 195; leaving vague, 201; position in bridi, 195; unspecified, 201 -->
<!-- ^^   seltcita sumti: definition (see also modal sumti), 195 -->
<indexterm><primary>seltcita sumti</primary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>modal sumti</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>la meiris.</quote>and 
    <quote>la betis.</quote>respectively) would become attached to the bridi as a whole, producing a very different translation. 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section10-example8" />would become:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-5QHA">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e10d9" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section10-example9" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>la frank. nelci la meiris. seme'a la betis.</jbo>
        <gloss>Frank likes Mary is-less-than Betty.</gloss>
        <en>Frank's liking Mary is less than Betty.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>which compares a liking with a person, and is therefore nonsense.</para>
    <para>Pure comparison, which states only the comparative information but says nothing about whether Frank actually likes either Mary or Betty (he may like neither, but dislike Betty less), would be expressed differently, as:</para>
<!-- ^^   comparison: claims related to based on form, 204 -->
<indexterm><primary>comparison</primary></indexterm>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-AAQp">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e10d10" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section10-example10" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>le ni la frank. nelci la betis. cu zmadu</jbo>
        <gloss>le ni la frank. nelci la meiris.</gloss>
        <gloss>The quantity-of Frank's liking Betty is-more-than</gloss>
        <en>the quantity-of Frank's liking Mary.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>The mechanisms explained in this section are appropriate to many modals other than 
    <quote>semau</quote>and 
    <quote>seme'a</quote>. Some other modals that are often associated with relative phrases are: 
    <quote>seba'i</quote>( 
<!-- ^^   seba'i, 204 -->
<indexterm><primary>seba'i</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>instead of</quote>), 
    <quote>ci'u</quote>( 
<!-- ^^   ci'u, 204 -->
<indexterm><primary>ci'u</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>on scale</quote>), 
    <quote>de'i</quote>( 
<!-- ^^   de'i, 204 -->
<indexterm><primary>de'i</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>dated</quote>), 
    <quote>du'i</quote>( 
<!-- ^^   du'i, 204 -->
<indexterm><primary>du'i</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>as much as</quote>). Some BAI tags can be used equally well in relative phrases or attached to bridi; others seem useful only attached to bridi. But it is also possible that the usefulness of particular BAI modals is an English-speaker bias, and that speakers of other languages may find other BAIs useful in divergent ways.</para>
    <para>Note: The uses of modals discussed in this section are applicable both to BAI modals and to 
    <quote>fi'o</quote>-plus-selbri modals.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section11">
    <title>Mixed modal connection</title>
    <para>It is possible to mix logical connection (explained in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter14" />) with modal connection, in a way that simultaneously asserts the logical connection and the modal relationship. Consider the sentences:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-4qz4">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e11d1" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section11-example1" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi nelci do .ije mi nelci la djein.</jbo>
        <en>I like you. And I like Jane.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>which is a logical connection, and</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-6EE5">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e11d2" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section11-example2" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi nelci do .iki'ubo mi nelci la djein.</jbo>
        <en>I like you. Justified-by I like Jane.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>The meanings of 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section11-example1" />and 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section11-example2" />can be simultaneously expressed by combining the two compound cmavo, thus:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-W3Le">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e11d3" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section11-example3" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi nelci do .ijeki'ubo mi nelci la djein.</jbo>
        <en>I like you. And justified-by I like Jane.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Here the two sentences 
    <quote>mi nelci do</quote>and 
    <quote>mi nelci la djein.</quote>are simultaneously asserted, their logical connection is asserted, and their causal relationship is asserted. The logical connective 
    <quote>je</quote>comes before the modal 
    <quote>ki'u</quote>in all such mixed connections.</para>
<!-- ^^   ki'u, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>ki'u</primary></indexterm>
    <para>Since 
    <quote>mi nelci do</quote>and 
    <quote>mi nelci la djein.</quote>differ only in the final sumti, we can transform 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section11-example3" />into a mixed sumti connection:</para>
<!-- ^^   sumti connection: afterthought, 340; forethought, 341 -->
<indexterm><primary>sumti connection</primary></indexterm>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-gE1z">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e11d4" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section11-example4" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi nelci do .eki'ubo la djein.</jbo>
        <en>I like you and/because Jane.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Note that this connection is an afterthought one. Mixed connectives are always afterthought; forethought connectives must be either logical or modal.</para>
<!-- ^^   forethought connectives: with tense, 364 -->
<indexterm><primary>forethought connectives</primary></indexterm>
    <para>There are numerous other afterthought logical and non-logical connectives that can have modal information planted within them. For example, a bridi-tail connected version of 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section11-example4" />would be:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-7LmA">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e11d5" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section11-example5" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi nelci do gi'eki'ubo nelci la djein.</jbo>
        <en>I like you and/because like Jane.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>The following three complex examples all mean the same thing.</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-D6iy">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e11d6" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section11-example6" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e11d7" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section11-example7" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e11d8" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section11-example8" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi bevri le dakli</jbo>
        <gloss>.ijeseri'abo tu'e mi bevri le gerku .ijadu'ibo mi bevri le mlatu [tu'u]</gloss>
        <gloss>I carry the sack.</gloss>
        <gloss>And [effect] (I carry the dog. And/or [equal] I carry the cat.)</gloss>
        <gloss>I carry the sack.</gloss>
        <en>As a result I carry the dog or I carry the cat, equally.</en>
        <jbo>mi bevri le dakli</jbo>
        <gloss>gi'eseri'ake bevri le gerku gi'adu'ibo bevri le mlatu [ke'e]</gloss>
        <gloss>I carry the sack</gloss>
        <gloss>and [effect] (carry the dog and/or [equal] carry the cat).</gloss>
        <en>I carry the sack and as a result carry the dog or carry the cat equally.</en>
        <jbo>mi bevri le dakli</jbo>
        <gloss>.eseri'ake le gerku .adu'ibo le mlatu [ke'e]</gloss>
        <gloss>I carry the sack</gloss>
        <gloss>and [effect] (the cat and/or [equal] the dog).</gloss>
        <en>I carry the sack, and as a result the cat or the dog equally.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>In 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section11-example6" />, the 
    <quote>tu'e ... tu'u</quote>brackets are the equivalent of the 
    <quote>ke ... ke'e</quote>brackets in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section11-example7" />and 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section11-example8" />, because 
    <quote>ke ... ke'e</quote>cannot extend across more than one sentence. It would also be possible to change the 
    <quote>.ijeseri'abo</quote>to 
    <quote>.ije seri'a</quote>, which would show that the 
    <quote>tu'e ... tu'u</quote>portion was an effect, but would not pin down the 
    <quote>mi bevri le dakli</quote>portion as the cause. It is legal for a modal (or a tense; see 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter10" />) to modify the whole of a 
    <quote>tu'e ... tu'u</quote>construct.</para>
    <para>Note: The uses of modals discussed in this section are applicable both to BAI modals and to 
    <quote>fi'o</quote>-plus-selbri modals.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section12">
    <title>Modal conversion: JAI</title>
    <para>The following cmavo are discussed in this section:</para>
    <cmavo-list>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>jai</cmavo>
        <selmaho>JAI</selmaho>
        <description>modal conversion</description>
<!-- ^^   modal conversion: access to original first place with fai, 206; grammar of, 206; place structure of, 206; with no modal specified, 206 -->
<indexterm><primary>modal conversion</primary></indexterm>
      </cmavo-entry>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>fai</cmavo>
        <selmaho>FA</selmaho>
        <description>modal place structure tag</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
    </cmavo-list>
    <para>So far, conversion of numbered bridi places with SE and the addition of modal places with BAI have been two entirely separate operations. However, it is possible to convert a selbri in such a way that, rather than exchanging two numbered places, a modal place is made into a numbered place. For example,</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-KMMX">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e12d1" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section12-example1" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi cusku bau la lojban.</jbo>
        <en>I express [something] in-language Lojban.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>has an explicit x1 place occupied by 
    <quote>mi</quote>and an explicit 
    <quote>bau</quote>place occupied by 
    <quote>la lojban.</quote>To exchange these two, we use a modal conversion operator consisting of 
<!-- ^^   modal conversion: access to original first place with fai, 206; grammar of, 206; place structure of, 206; with no modal specified, 206 -->
<indexterm><primary>modal conversion</primary></indexterm>
    <quote>jai</quote>(of selma'o JAI) followed by the modal cmavo. Thus, the modal conversion of 
<!-- ^^   modal conversion: access to original first place with fai, 206; grammar of, 206; place structure of, 206; with no modal specified, 206 -->
<indexterm><primary>modal conversion</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   modal cmavo: basis in gismu place structure, 210; list of irregular derivation, 209; position relative to selbri, 104; regular form for derivation, 208; table with English equivalents, 210 -->
<indexterm><primary>modal cmavo</primary></indexterm>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section12-example1" />is:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-KjyW">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e12d2" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section12-example2" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>la lojban. jai bau cusku fai mi</jbo>
        <en>Lojban is-the-language-of-expression used-by me.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>In 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section12-example2" />, the modal place 
    <quote>la lojban.</quote>has become the x1 place of the new selbri 
    <quote>jai bau cusku</quote>. What has happened to the old x1 place? There is no numbered place for it to move to, so it moves to a special 
    <quote>unnumbered place</quote>marked by the tag 
    <quote>fai</quote>of selma'o FA.</para>
    <para>Note: For the purposes of place numbering, 
    <quote>fai</quote>behaves like 
    <quote>fi'a</quote>; it does not affect the numbering of the other places around it.</para>
<!-- ^^   fi'a, 191; effect on subsequent untagged sumti, 192 -->
<indexterm><primary>fi'a</primary></indexterm>
    <para>Like SE conversions, JAI conversions are especially convenient in descriptions. We may refer to 
    <quote>the language of an expression</quote>as 
    <quote>le jai bau cusku</quote>, for example.</para>
    <para>In addition, it is grammatical to use 
    <quote>jai</quote>without a following modal. This usage is not related to modals, but is explained here for completeness. The effect of 
    <quote>jai</quote>by itself is to send the x1 place, which should be an abstraction, into the 
    <quote>fai</quote>position, and to raise one of the sumti from the abstract sub-bridi into the x1 place of the main bridi. This feature is discussed in more detail in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter11" />. The following two examples mean the same thing:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-DSQS">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e12d3" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section12-example3" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e12d4" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section12-example4" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>le nu mi lebna le cukta cu se krinu le nu mi viska le cukta</jbo>
        <gloss>The event-of (I take the book) is-justified-by the event-of (I see the book).</gloss>
        <en>My taking the book is justified by my seeing it.</en>
        <jbo>mi jai se krinu le nu mi viska le cukta kei</jbo>
        <gloss>[fai le nu mi lebna le cukta]</gloss>
        <gloss>I am-justified by the event-of (I see the book)</gloss>
        <gloss>[namely, the event-of (I take the book)]</gloss>
        <en>I am justified in taking the book by seeing the book.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section12-example4" />, with the bracketed part omitted, allows us to say that 
    <quote>I am justified</quote>whereas in fact it is my action that is justified. This construction is vague, but useful in representing natural-language methods of expression.</para>
    <para>Note: The uses of modals discussed in this section are applicable both to BAI modals and to 
    <quote>fi'o</quote>-plus-selbri modals.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section13">
    <title>Modal negation</title>
    <para>Negation is explained in detail in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter15" />. There are two forms of negation in Lojban: contradictory and scalar negation. Contradictory negation expresses what is false, whereas scalar negation says that some alternative to what has been stated is true. A simple example is the difference between 
    <quote>John didn't go to Paris</quote>(contradictory negation) and 
    <quote>John went to (somewhere) other than Paris</quote>(scalar negation).</para>
    <para>Contradictory negation involving BAI cmavo is performed by appending 
    <quote>-nai</quote>(of selma'o NAI) to the BAI. A common use of modals with 
    <quote>-nai</quote>is to deny a causal relationship:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-ej84">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e13d1" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section13-example1" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi nelci do mu'inai le nu do nelci mi</jbo>
        <en>I like you, but not because you like me.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section13-example1" />denies that the relationship between my liking you (which is asserted) and your liking me (which is not asserted) is one of motivation. Nothing is said about whether you like me or not, merely that that hypothetical liking is not the motivation for my liking you.</para>
    <para>Scalar negation is achieved by prefixing 
    <quote>na'e</quote>(of selma'o NAhE), or any of the other cmavo of NAhE, to the BAI cmavo.</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-9WC5">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e13d2" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section13-example2" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>le spati cu banro na'emu'i le nu</jbo>
        <gloss>do djacu dunda fi le spati</gloss>
        <gloss>The plant grows other-than-motivated-by the event-of</gloss>
        <en>you water-give to the plant.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section13-example2" />says that the relationship between the plant's growth and your watering it is not one of motivation: the plant is not motivated to grow, as plants are not something which can have motivation as a rule. Implicitly, some other relationship between watering and growth exists, but 
<!-- ^^   plants: use of fu'ivla for specific, 61 -->
<indexterm><primary>plants</primary></indexterm>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section13-example2" />doesn't say what it is (presumably 
    <quote>ri'a</quote>).</para>
    <para>Note: Modals made with 
    <quote>fi'o</quote>plus a selbri cannot be negated directly. The selbri can itself be negated either with contradictory or with scalar negation, however.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section14">
    <title>Sticky modals</title>
    <para>The following cmavo is discussed in this section:</para>
    <cmavo-list>
      <cmavo-entry>
        <cmavo>ki</cmavo>
        <selmaho>KI</selmaho>
        <description>stickiness flag</description>
      </cmavo-entry>
    </cmavo-list>
    <para>Like tenses, modals can be made persistent from the bridi in which they appear to all following bridi. The effect of this 
    <quote>stickiness</quote>is to make the modal, along with its following sumti, act as if it appeared in every successive bridi. Stickiness is put into effect by following the modal (but not any following sumti) with the cmavo 
    <quote>ki</quote>of selma'o KI. For example,</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-1UGf">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e14d1" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section14-example1" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi tavla bau la lojban. bai ki tu'a la frank.</jbo>
        <gloss>.ibabo mi tavla bau la gliban.</gloss>
        <gloss>I speak in-language Lojban compelled-by some-property-of Frank.</gloss>
        <en>Afterward, I speak in-language English.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>means the same as:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-txFr">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e14d2" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section14-example2" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi tavla bau la lojban. bai tu'a la frank.</jbo>
        <gloss>.ibabo mi tavla bau la gliban.</gloss>
        <gloss>bai tu'a la frank.</gloss>
        <gloss>I speak in-language Lojban compelled-by some-property-of Frank.</gloss>
        <gloss>Afterward, I speak in-language English</gloss>
        <en>compelled-by some-property-of Frank.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>In 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section14-example1" />, 
    <quote>bai</quote>is made sticky, and so Frank's compelling is made applicable to every following bridi. 
    <quote>bau</quote>is not sticky, and so the language may vary from bridi to bridi, and if not specified in a particular bridi, no assumption can safely be made about its value.</para>
    <para>To cancel stickiness, use the form 
    <quote>BAI ki ku</quote>, which stops any modal value for the specified BAI from being passed to the next bridi. To cancel stickiness for all modals simultaneously, and also for any sticky tenses that exist ( 
    <quote>ki</quote>is used for both modals and tenses), use 
    <quote>ki</quote>by itself, either before the selbri or (in the form 
    <quote>ki ku</quote>) anywhere in the bridi:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-sYdo">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e14d3" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section14-example3" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>mi ki tavla</jbo>
        <en>I speak (no implication about language or compulsion).</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Note: Modals made with 
    <quote>fi'o</quote>-plus-selbri cannot be made sticky. This is an unfortunate, but unavoidable, restriction.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section15">
    <title>Logical and non-logical connection of modals</title>
<!-- ^^   non-logical connection: and elidability of terminators, 354; in mathematical expressions, 361; in tanru, distinguishing from connection of sumti, 354; of individuals into mass, 355; of individuals into set, 355; of modals, 208; of operands, 455; of operators, 455; of sumti, distinguishing from connection in tanru, 354; of termsets, 357 -->
<indexterm><primary>non-logical connection</primary></indexterm>
    <para>Logical and non-logical connectives are explained in detail in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter14" />. For the purposes of this chapter, it suffices to point out that a logical (or non-logical) connection between two bridi which differ only in a modal can be reduced to a single bridi with a connective between the modals. As a result, 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section15-example1" />and 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section15-example2" />mean the same thing:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-2NAa">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e15d1" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section15-example1" />
        <anchor xml:id="c9e15d2" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section15-example2" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>la frank. bajra seka'a le zdani .ije la frank. bajra teka'a le zdani</jbo>
        <gloss>Frank runs with-destination the house. And Frank runs with-origin the house.</gloss>
        <en>Frank runs to the house, and Frank runs from the house.</en>
        <jbo>la frank. bajra seka'a je teka'a le zdani</jbo>
        <gloss>Frank runs with-destination and with-origin the house.</gloss>
        <en>Frank runs to and from the house.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>Neither example implies whether a single act, or two acts, of running is referred to. To compel the sentence to refer to a single act of running, you can use the form:</para>
    <example role="interlinear-gloss-example" xml:id="random-id-b0LW">
      <title>
        <anchor xml:id="c9e15d3" />
        <anchor xml:id="cll_chapter9-section15-example3" />
      </title>
      <interlinear-gloss>
        <jbo>la frank. bajra seka'a le zdani ce'e teka'a le zdani</jbo>
        <en>Frank runs with-destination the house [joined-to] with-origin the-house.</en>
      </interlinear-gloss>
    </example>
    <para>The cmavo 
    <quote>ce'e</quote>creates a termset containing two terms (termsets are explained in 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter14" />and 
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter16" />). When a termset contains more than one modal tag derived from a single BAI, the convention is that the two tags are derived from a common event.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section16">
    <title>CV'V cmavo of selma'o BAI with irregular forms</title>
    <para>There are 65 cmavo of selma'o BAI, of which all but one ( 
    <quote>do'e</quote>, discussed in 
<!-- ^^   do'e, 197; compared with English of, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>do'e</primary></indexterm>
    <xref linkend="cll_chapter9-section6" />), are derived directly from selected gismu. Of these 64 cmavo, 36 are entirely regular and have the form CV'V, where C is the first consonant of the corresponding gismu, and the Vs are the two vowels of the gismu. The remaining BAI cmavo, which are irregular in one way or another, are listed in the table below. The table is divided into sub-tables according to the nature of the exception; some cmavo appear in more than one sub-table, and are so noted.</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
   cmavo    gismu        comments

    Monosyllables of the form CVV:

    bai     bapli
    bau     bangu
    cau     claxu
    fau     fasnu
    gau     gasnu
    kai     ckaji        uses 2nd consonant of gismu
    mau     zmadu        uses 2nd consonant of gismu
<!-- ^^   mau, 203, 432; avoiding in favor of seme'a, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>mau</primary></indexterm>
    koi     korbi
    rai     traji        uses 2nd consonant of gismu
    sau     sarcu
    tai     tamsmi       based on lujvo, not gismu
    zau     zanru

    Second consonant of the gismu as the C:
        (the gismu is always of the form CCVCV)

    ga'a    zgana
    kai     ckaji        has CVV form (monosyllable)
    ki'i    ckini
    la'u    klani        has irregular 2nd V
    le'a    klesi        has irregular 2nd V
    mau     zmadu        has CVV form (monosyllable)
<!-- ^^   mau, 203, 432; avoiding in favor of seme'a, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>mau</primary></indexterm>
    me'e    cmene
    ra'a    srana
    ra'i    krasi
    rai     traji        has CVV form (monosyllable)
    ti'i    stidi
    tu'i    stuzi

    Irregular 2nd V:

    fi'e    finti
<!-- ^^   fi'e, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>fi'e</primary></indexterm>
    la'u    klani        uses 2nd consonant of gismu
    le'a    klesi        uses 2nd consonant of gismu
    ma'e    marji
    mu'u    mupli
    ti'u    tcika
    va'o    vanbi

    Special cases:

    ri'i    lifri        uses 3rd consonant of gismu
    tai     tamsmi       based on lujvo, not gismu
    va'u    xamgu        CV'V cmavo can't begin with 
<quote>x</quote>
</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cll_chapter9-section17">
    <title>Complete table of BAI cmavo with rough English equivalents</title>
    <para>The following table shows all the cmavo belonging to selma'o BAI, and has five columns. The first column is the cmavo itself; the second column is the gismu linked to it. The third column gives an English phrase which indicates the meaning of the cmavo; and the fourth column indicates its meaning when preceded by 
    <quote>se</quote>.</para>
    <para>For those cmavo with meaningful 
    <quote>te</quote>, 
    <quote>ve</quote>, and even 
    <quote>xe</quote>conversions (depending on the number of places of the underlying gismu), the meanings of these are shown on one or two extra rows following the primary row for that cmavo.</para>
    <para>It should be emphasized that the place structures of the gismu control the meanings of the BAI cmavo. The English phrases shown here are only suggestive, and are often too broad or too narrow to correctly specify what the acceptable range of uses for the modal tag are.</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
    ba'i    basti   replaced by                    instead of 
<!-- skip cmavo list automation -->
    bai     bapli   compelled by                   compelling
    bau     bangu   in language                    in language of
    be'i    benji   sent by                        transmitting
                    te=sent to                     ve=with transmit origin
                    xe=transmitted via
    ca'i    catni   by authority of                with authority over
    cau     claxu   lacked by                      without
    ci'e    ciste   in system                      with system function
                    te=of system components
    ci'o    cinmo   felt by                        feeling emotion
    ci'u    ckilu   on the scale                   on scale measuring
<!-- ^^   ci'u, 204 -->
<indexterm><primary>ci'u</primary></indexterm>
    cu'u    cusku   as said by                     expressing
<!-- ^^   cu'u, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>cu'u</primary></indexterm>
                    te=as told to                  ve=expressed in medium
    de'i    detri   dated                          on the same date as
<!-- ^^   de'i, 204 -->
<indexterm><primary>de'i</primary></indexterm>
    di'o    diklo   at the locus of                at specific locus
    do'e    -----   vaguely related to
<!-- ^^   do'e, 197; compared with English of, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>do'e</primary></indexterm>
    du'i    dunli   as much as                     equal to
<!-- ^^   dunli: contrasted with du, 163, 439 -->
<indexterm><primary>dunli</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   du'i, 204 -->
<indexterm><primary>du'i</primary></indexterm>
    du'o    djuno   according to                   knowing facts
                    te=knowing about
                    ve=under epistemology
    fa'e    fatne   reverse of                     in reversal of
    fau     fasnu   in the event of
    fi'e    finti   created by                     creating work
<!-- ^^   fi'e, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>fi'e</primary></indexterm>
                    te=created                     for purpose
    ga'a    zgana   to observer                    observing
                    te=observed                    by means
                    ve=observed under conditions
    gau     gasnu   with agent                     as agent in doing
    ja'e    jalge   resulting in                   results because of
    ja'i    javni   by rule                        by rule prescribing
    ji'e    jimte   up to limit                    as a limit of
    ji'o    jitro   under direction                controlling
    ji'u    jicmu   based on                       supporting
    ka'a    klama   gone to by                     with destination
<!-- ^^   ka'a, 196 -->
<indexterm><primary>ka'a</primary></indexterm>
                    te=with origin                 ve=via route
                    xe=by transport mode
    ka'i    krati   represented by                 on behalf of
    kai     ckaji   characterizing                 with property
    ki'i    ckini   as relation of                 related to
                    te=with relation
    ki'u    krinu   justified by                   with justified result
<!-- ^^   ki'u, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>ki'u</primary></indexterm>
    koi     korbi   bounded by                     as boundary of
                    te=bordering
    ku'u    kulnu   in culture                     in culture of
    la'u    klani   as quantity of                 in quantity
    le'a    klesi   in category                    as category of
                    te=defined by quality
    li'e    lidne   led by                         leading
    ma'e    marji   of material                    made from material
                    te=in material form of
    ma'i    manri   in reference frame             as a standard for
<!-- ^^   reference frame: specifying for direction tenses, 224 -->
<indexterm><primary>reference frame</primary></indexterm>
<!-- ^^   ma'i, 224 -->
<indexterm><primary>ma'i</primary></indexterm>
    mau     zmadu   exceeded by                    more than
<!-- ^^   mau, 203, 432; avoiding in favor of seme'a, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>mau</primary></indexterm>
    me'a    mleca   undercut by                    less than
<!-- ^^   me'a, 203; avoiding in favor of semau, 203 -->
<indexterm><primary>me'a</primary></indexterm>
    me'e    cmene   with name                      as a name for
                    te=as a name to
    mu'i    mukti   motivated by                   motive therefore
<!-- ^^   mu'i, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>mu'i</primary></indexterm>
    mu'u    mupli   exemplified by                 as an example of
    ni'i    nibli   entailed by                    entails
<!-- ^^   ni'i, 197 -->
<indexterm><primary>ni'i</primary></indexterm>
    pa'a    panra   in addition to                 similar to
                    te=similar in pattern
                    ve=similar by standard
    pa'u    pagbu   with component                 as a part of
    pi'o    pilno   used by                        using tool
<!-- ^^   pi'o, 195 -->
<indexterm><primary>pi'o</primary></indexterm>
    po'i    porsi   in the sequence                sequenced by rule
    pu'a    pluka   pleased by                     in order to please
    pu'e    pruce   by process                     processing from
                    te=processing into
                    ve=passing through stages
    ra'a    srana   pertained to by concerning
    ra'i    krasi   from source as an origin of
    rai     traji   with superlative               superlative in
                    te=at extreme                  ve=superlative among
    ri'a    rinka   caused by                      causing
    ri'i    lifri   experienced by                 experiencing
<!-- ^^   experienced: example, 316 -->
<indexterm><primary>experienced</primary></indexterm>
    sau     sarcu   requiring                      necessarily for
                    te=necessarily under conditions
    si'u    sidju   aided by                       assisting in
    ta'i    tadji   by method                      as a method for
    tai     tamsmi  as a form of                   in form
                    te=in form similar to
    ti'i    stidi   suggested by                   suggesting
                    te=suggested to
    ti'u    tcika   with time                      at the time of
    tu'i    stuzi   with site                      as location of
    va'o    vanbi   under conditions               as conditions for
    va'u    xamgu   benefiting from                with beneficiary
    zau     zanru   approved by                    approving
    zu'e    zukte   with actor                     with means to goal
                    te=with goal
</programlisting>
    <para>The lujvo 
    <quote>tamsmi</quote>on which 
    <quote>tai</quote>is based is derived from the tanru 
    <quote>tarmi simsa</quote>and has the place structure:</para>
    <programlisting xml:space="preserve">
       tamsmi: x1 has form x2, similar in form to x3 in property/quality x4
</programlisting>
    <para>This lujvo is employed because 
    <quote>tarmi</quote>does not have a place structure useful for the modal's purpose.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
